Hanson Weightman Baldwin Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Hanson Weightman Baldwin Papers 1920-1978
MSS61729
Baldwin, Hanson Weightman, 1903-1991
1,500 items
8 containers
3 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Author and editor. Correspondence, memoranda, minutes, reports, notes, typescripts, press releases, printed matter, and other papers pertaining primarily to Baldwin's naval career and his early years as a general assignment newspaper reporter.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Baldwin, Hanson Weightman, 1903-1991.
Organizations
Naval War College (U.S.); U.S. Naval Academy Alumni Association.; United States Naval Academy.; United States. Naval Reserve--Officers.; United States. Navy--Officers.
Subjects
American newspapers--Maryland--Baltimore.; American newspapers--New York (State)--New York.
Titles
New York times.; Sun (Baltimore, Md.: 1837)
Occupations
Authors.; Newspaper editors.
Provenance
The papers of Hanson Weightman Baldwin, author and editor, were deposited in the Library of Congress by the Naval Historical Foundation in 1984 and converted to a gift in 1998.
Related Materials
The principal collection of the Hanson Weightman Baldwin Papers is located in the Beinecke Library at Yale University, while a smaller collection of papers exists at the George C. Marshall Research Foundation Library, Lexington, Virginia.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Hanson Weightman Baldwin are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1903, Mar. 22 Born, Baltimore, Md.
1924 B.S., United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md.
1924 1927 Naval officer, sea duty along the East Coast, in the Caribbean, and in Europe
1927 Resigned from active duty
1928 1929 Police and general assignment reporter, Baltimore Sun
1929 1937 General assignment reporter, New York Times
1931 Married Helen Bruce
1933 Resigned Naval Reserve commission
1937 1942 Military and naval correspondent, New York Times
1942 Published Strategy for Victory. New York: W. W. Norton
1942 1968 Military affairs editor, New York Times
1943 Awarded the Pulitzer Prize
1944 Awarded Distinguished Service Medal, Syracuse University, Syracuse, N.Y.
1958 Published The Great Arms Race. New York: Praeger
1969 1971 President, United States Naval Academy Alumni Association
1970 Published Strategy for Tomorrow. New York: Harper & Row
1991, Nov. 13 Died, Roxbury, Conn.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Hanson Weightman Baldwin (1903-1991) date from 1920 to 1978 and most prominently document his student years at the United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Maryland, along with his subsequent tour of active duty in the navy, his early years as a general assignment newspaper reporter, and his participation as an active member of both the United States Naval Academy Alumni Association and the Naval War College, Washington, D.C. The papers are organized into the following series: Correspondence, Subject File, Speeches and Writings File, and Miscellany.
The Correspondence series contains letters exchanged between Baldwin and his parents which provide details of Baldwin's years at the United States Naval Academy and describe the atmosphere of academy life in the period immediately following World War I. A file containing report cards and other school records from his student days is located in the Subject File, while the Miscellany series includes several personal notebooks kept by Baldwin at the academy.
Following his graduation from the Naval Academy, Baldwin served as an officer aboard the battleship Texas and the destroyer Breck. In 1928 he began his career as a newspaper reporter after having resigned from active naval duty the previous year. Baldwin's letters to his parents in the Correspondence series provide information on his life as a young naval officer and also on his early years as a general assignment reporter, first with the Baltimore Sun in 1928 and a year later with the New York Times, the paper with which he would be associated for the remainder of his career. Although the Correspondence also contains letters to and from friends and former shipmates which further document this period of Baldwin's life, there are few letters in the series which illuminate his newspaper career after his appointment in 1937 by the Times as the first full-time military correspondent, and later military editor, on an American newspaper.
Baldwin's service as a commissioned officer in the navy, both on active duty and in the Naval Reserve, is also documented in the Subject File. Records in this file concerning his resignation in 1933 give evidence to the conflict which arose between Baldwin's position as a Naval Academy graduate and naval officer, whose code required conduct loyal to the service, and his role as a newspaper reporter, whose commitment to objective and unprejudiced reporting demanded freedom of expression, when an article written by Baldwin contained information that was deemed sensitive by naval authorities. Explaining his position in a memorandum to the Chief of the Bureau of Navigation dated 1 March 1933, Baldwin wrote, "Loyalty cannot be interpreted from my viewpoint as preventing me the free and unabridged statement of fact or expression of opinion."
The Subject File also contains records relating to Baldwin's appointment as president of the United States Naval Academy Alumni Association and to his membership on the board of advisors of the Naval War College. Baldwin's literary manuscripts, few of which are included in the collection, are filed in the Speeches and Writings File.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in four series:
Correspondence, 1920-1977
Subject File, 1920-1978
Speeches and Writings File, 1929-1973
Miscellany, 1920-1970
Container List
- Correspondence, 1920-1977 (Box 1)
  Letters sent and received, including correspondence with family members, postcards, and miscellaneous enclosures.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1920-1977, undated, (4 folders) (Box 1)
- Subject File, 1920-1978 (Box 2-6)
  Correspondence, memoranda, notes, printed matter, press releases, reports, school records, minutes of meetings, documents, and miscellaneous items.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Arnheiter-Alexander investigation, 1967-1968 (Box 2)
  - "Caribbean" book research (Box 2)
  - Korean War, 1950-1951, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Naval War College, Washington, D.C. (Box 2)
    - Advanced research program (Box 2)
    - Board of advisors, 1972-1975 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1970-1975, undated (Box 3)
    - Correspondence course, 1924-1925 (Box 3)
    - Memoranda for the president of the college, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Miscellany, 1971-1975 (Box 3)
  - President's Maritime Advisory Committee, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
  - Scorpion (Warship), 1968 (Box 3)
  - United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md., 1920-1924 (Box 3)
  - United States Naval Academy Alumni Association (Box 4)
    - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - 1967, June-1971, May, (4 folders) (Box 4)
      - 1971, June-1978, Feb., undated (Box 5)
    - Meetings (Box 5)
      - Board of trustees, 1968-1971 (Box 5)
      - Business committee, 1969 (Box 5)
      - Miscellany (Box 5)
    - Michelson, Albert A., nomination to Hall of Fame for Great Americans, New York University, New York, N.Y. (Box 5)
    - Miscellany (Box 5)
    - Recruiting campaign, 1969-1970 (Box 5)
  - United States Navy (Box 6)
    - Documents and records, 1924-1934, undated (Box 6)
    - Resignation, 1933-1934 (Box 6)
- Speeches and Writings File, 1929-1973 (Box 6-7)
  Typescripts, printed matter, and notes relating to the speeches and writings of Hanson Baldwin and others.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Articles and other writings (Box 6)
    - Printed copies, 1930-1950, undated (Box 6)
    - Typescripts (Box 6)
      - 1929-1970 (Box 6)
      - Undated, (1 folder) (Box 6, Box 7)
  - Speeches, 1973, undated (Box 7)
  - Speeches and writings by others, 1917-1972, undated (Box 7)
- Miscellany, 1920-1970 (Box 7-8)
  Newspaper clippings, printed matter, notes and notebooks, and cards.
  - Cards (Box 7)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1933-1968, undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Notebooks, 1920-1929 (Box 8)
  - Notes (Box 8)
  - Printed matter, 1930-1970, undated (Box 8)